<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Rich Code]]></title>
  <link href="http://rjmccluskey.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rjmccluskey.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-07T21:59:02-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://rjmccluskey.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rich McCluskey]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dev Bootcamp Is More Than Just Learning to Code]]></title>
    <link href="http://rjmccluskey.github.io/blog/2014/09/16/dev-bootcamp-is-more-than-just-learning-to-code/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-16T22:46:38-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://rjmccluskey.github.io/blog/2014/09/16/dev-bootcamp-is-more-than-just-learning-to-code</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have officially started Phase 0 of <a href="http://devbootcamp.com">devbootcamp</a> and right away we are being challenged to research mindfulness, productivity, and time management. At first I was a little apprehensive to do this because I was really itching to get straight to writing code, but I continued on and actually discovered some really awesome stuff!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The next ~18 weeks are gonna be really intense. I knew they would be before I even applied to DBC, but now that I have started the curriculum I am beginning to truly understand what that means. I’m not gonna lie. It’s scary. But I’m so pumped at the same time! And I realize that we are spending time to learn things like mindfulness so that we not only keep our sanity, but also to develop ourselves as human beings. You might even say that DBC isn’t only about web development, but self development too.</p>

<p>So what am I gonna do during Phase 0 to keep myself on tract and reduce stress? First, I want to dabble with meditation and what better way to learn to meditate than to use a web app! <a href="https://www.headspace.com/">Headspace</a> is like a “gym membership for the mind” and offers quick exercises to get you meditating. Second, I’m gonna try to implement the <a href="http://pomodorotechnique.com/">Pomodoro Technique</a> into my studies. If you’ve never heard of this before, it basically involves working in 25 minute increments with time to reflect on your work. And thirdly, I want to give myself a little slack. This <a href="http://paidtoexist.com/counterintuitive-productivity/">article</a> on productivity says it best: “Relax your expectations of constant, never-ceasing production. Instead, focus your energies on how you want to feel and what you need to operate with greatness… The key is in learning to identify and honor your natural rhythms. Listen and lean into whatever you’re being pulled to.”</p>

<p>Alright, I’m off to bed! Hopefully my next entry will have some actual code in it! ;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Taking a Leap]]></title>
    <link href="http://rjmccluskey.github.io/blog/2014/09/09/taking-a-leap/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-09T21:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://rjmccluskey.github.io/blog/2014/09/09/taking-a-leap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Three years ago I graduated from Cal Poly with a degree in Civil Engineering. In case you didn’t already do the math, three years ago was 2011 and the economy was horrible. I didn’t know <em>anyone</em> in my major that had a job lined up. On top of all that, I wasn’t even sure if civil engineering was really what I wanted to do. Go figure, an 18 year old entering college straight from high school had trouble choosing a major…</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>But I didn’t want to admit “defeat” and I pretended that I was destined to be a civil engineer. I pushed past my gut feelings, got certified as an Engineer in Training (EIT) and eventually found a job. And for some time things were pretty good!</p>

<p>After a while, however, I started feeling an itch. And it didn’t go away. I wanted something different; something more creative but still technical. I wanted to feel passionate about my work and I wanted to have fun. I am sure there are civil engineers out there that feel this way about their work, but that simply was not me. I finally admitted to myself that it was ok to change my mind.</p>

<p>So, I began searching. I began noticing what made me feel excited. I purposely resisted falling into mediocracy. I started to learn some basic programming, and I really liked it! Pretty quickly I realized that writing code could be exactly what I was looking for in a career!  Learning on my own was going great but I knew that if I really wanted to take this leap and switch careers I would personally need more structure and mentorship. I had heard of “bootcamp” courses that taught programming languages in an incredibly short amount of time and as I researched this possibility I eventually found <a href="http://devbootcamp.com/">Dev Bootcamp</a>. I applied, and I got in!</p>

<p>In less than a week I embark on “Phase 0” of this program and I couldn’t be more excited. As part of my journey I thought it would be useful to blog about my experience so that I have a reference to look back on. I’ve never done anything like this before, but I want this to be public so that hopefully I inspire someone else to find more passion in their career.</p>

<p>So here it goes!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
