<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Javascript | Rich Code]]></title>
  <link href="http://rjmccluskey.github.io/blog/categories/javascript/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rjmccluskey.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-25T23:32:43-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://rjmccluskey.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rich McCluskey]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Iterations - Ruby vs JavaScript]]></title>
    <link href="http://rjmccluskey.github.io/blog/2014/11/02/iterations-ruby-vs-javascript/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-02T12:01:25-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://rjmccluskey.github.io/blog/2014/11/02/iterations-ruby-vs-javascript</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;ve started learning JavaScript this week and I have mixed feelings about it. At first it was just a pain in the ass. I&#8217;ve gotten pretty used to the wonders of ruby and how simple it can be. JavaScript on the other hand, can be pretty tough for a beginner. But as I got going I started to really like it because it is really fun to manipulate HTML elements. Anyways, to show you a little comparison between ruby and JS let&#8217;s take a look at how we can iterate through an array in both languages.</p>


<!-- more -->


<h3>Ruby</h3>




<p>If you are using ruby and you have an array object, you can do something to each of the values in that array using the <span class="code">each</span> method. If that&#8217;s not straightforward I don&#8217;t know what is! Let me show you how it works with an example:</p>




<pre class="code-window">
# Ruby

array = [1,2,3,4,5]
array.each { |value| puts value }

# 1
# 2
# 3
# 4
# 5</pre>




<p>This built in method knows how to cycle though the array automatically. Once you get used to the syntax there really isn&#8217;t much to think about. Of course this is a simple example and it can get much more complicated but you get the idea.</p>




<h3>JavaScript</h3>




<p>Unfortunately, there is nothing built into JS to iterate as easy as we can in ruby. So far, the best way I&#8217;ve found to iterate as we did with the example above is by using a <span class="code">for</span> loop. Let&#8217;s do the exact same iteration in JS:</p>




<pre class="code-window">
// JavaScript

var array = [1,2,3,4,5];
for (var count = 0; count < array.length; count++) {
  console.log(array[count]);
}

// 1
// 2
// 3
// 4
// 5</pre>




<p>A quick comparison shows that there&#8217;s definitely a little more to think about when iterating in JS. Making our array is pretty similar except we use the keyword <span class="code">var</span> and we need a semi-colon at the end of the statement. Our <span class="code">for</span> loop takes three expressions. The first creates a new local variable <span class="code">count</span> and assigns an initial value of 0 to it. The second expression is used so that the loop knows when to stop. And the third expression adds 1 to <span class="code">count</span> after each loop. I think it&#8217;s pretty obvious that ruby wins when it comes to ease of iterating.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
