<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: General | Rich Code]]></title>
  <link href="http://rjmccluskey.github.io/blog/categories/general/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rjmccluskey.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-07T21:32:11-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://rjmccluskey.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rich McCluskey]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Taking a Leap]]></title>
    <link href="http://rjmccluskey.github.io/blog/2014/09/09/taking-a-leap/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-09T21:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://rjmccluskey.github.io/blog/2014/09/09/taking-a-leap</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Three years ago I graduated from Cal Poly with a degree in Civil Engineering. In case you didn’t already do the math, three years ago was 2011 and the economy was horrible. I didn’t know <em>anyone</em> in my major that had a job lined up. On top of all that, I wasn’t even sure if civil engineering was really what I wanted to do. Go figure, an 18 year old entering college straight from high school had trouble choosing a major…</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>But I didn’t want to admit “defeat” and I pretended that I was destined to be a civil engineer. I pushed past my gut feelings, got certified as an Engineer in Training (EIT) and eventually found a job. And for some time things were pretty good!</p>

<p>After a while, however, I started feeling an itch. And it didn’t go away. I wanted something different; something more creative but still technical. I wanted to feel passionate about my work and I wanted to have fun. I am sure there are civil engineers out there that feel this way about their work, but that simply was not me. I finally admitted to myself that it was ok to change my mind.</p>

<p>So, I began searching. I began noticing what made me feel excited. I purposely resisted falling into mediocracy. I started to learn some basic programming, and I really liked it! Pretty quickly I realized that writing code could be exactly what I was looking for in a career!  Learning on my own was going great but I knew that if I really wanted to take this leap and switch careers I would personally need more structure and mentorship. I had heard of “bootcamp” courses that taught programming languages in an incredibly short amount of time and as I researched this possibility I eventually found <a href="http://devbootcamp.com/">Dev Bootcamp</a>. I applied, and I got in!</p>

<p>In less than a week I embark on “Phase 0” of this program and I couldn’t be more excited. As part of my journey I thought it would be useful to blog about my experience so that I have a reference to look back on. I’ve never done anything like this before, but I want this to be public so that hopefully I inspire someone else to find more passion in their career.</p>

<p>So here it goes!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
