<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: General | Rich Code]]></title>
  <link href="http://rjmccluskey.github.io/blog/categories/general/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rjmccluskey.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-19T12:28:42-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://rjmccluskey.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rich McCluskey]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I'm a Programmer]]></title>
    <link href="http://rjmccluskey.github.io/blog/2015/02/12/im-a-programmer/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-12T18:58:39-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://rjmccluskey.github.io/blog/2015/02/12/im-a-programmer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You&rsquo;ll notice a pretty big gap in time between this post and the last post. Well, that&rsquo;s because I was working my ass off at Dev Bootcamp! OK, I probably could&rsquo;ve still blogged but the reality is that it&rsquo;s hard for me to consistently write. But now that I&rsquo;ve graduated from DBC and I&rsquo;m looking for jobs I thought, what better time to start again?! There&rsquo;s so much I could talk about but I want to begin with this: <em>I am a programmer!</em></p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Am I programmer because I graduated from a coding school and magically became one that very day? &hellip; No. That&rsquo;s not what I am trying to say and I probably could&rsquo;ve called myself one much before that. But I&rsquo;m writing this now because being away from DBC and on my own has given me time to reflect. It has also given me time to continue to code and continue to learn. Being surrounded by tons of like minded people with the same general goal at DBC makes it pretty easy to stay motivated. But what happens when we leave? Any accountability has to come from myself, and to be honest I think that I&rsquo;ve done pretty well. I still want to code, I still want to improve, and I sure as hell still want to do this professionally. I began to apply to jobs, I reinvented my website, and I am jumping on an open source project (more to come on this!). Being away from DBC while still finding the same motivation to code is why I&rsquo;m a programmer.</p>

<p>So I guess this is me grabbing my identity and shouting it out to the world! I&rsquo;m so excited for the future and what it holds.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Do You Have a Question?]]></title>
    <link href="http://rjmccluskey.github.io/blog/2014/11/16/do-you-have-a-question/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-16T12:17:30-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://rjmccluskey.github.io/blog/2014/11/16/do-you-have-a-question</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Tomorrow is the big day. I start Phase 1 of <a href="http://devbootcamp.com">DBC</a> which means that the learning switches from remote to in-person and the real work begins. I&#8217;m so excited, a little nervous, really happy, but also kinda sad that I&#8217;ll be away from some of the people I love for a little while. Anyways, DBC is awesome because our education here is by no means traditional. In fact, a lot of it is up to us students asking for the right things. If we need help on something we need to ask for it because we&#8217;re gonna be moving fast! It&#8217;s really important that to get good answers, you need to ask good questions. So let&#8217;s talk about how to ask good technical questions.</p>


<!-- more -->


<p>So what makes a good question? Wait&#8230; was that good question? Just messing ;) I think the very first thing you need in order to ask a good question is to do as much research on your own within a reasonable time frame. If you&#8217;re chasing down random links on Google and not finding anything helpful then you&#8217;re pretty safe to start asking questions. This first step is important because it helps you to fully understand exactly what it is that you&#8217;re having trouble with.</p>




<p>Now that you know exactly what the problem is, you need to present it in a short and specific way. When posting a question online, this would involve the title of your post. Obviously since it is a title, it will be short but that doesn&#8217;t mean you should be too general. Imagine that you are trying to ask your question to your really busy boss. Be short and straight to the point with the title. If you&#8217;re asking a question in person, you don&#8217;t exactly have a title (unless you write it on a sticky note and put it on your head). So you can skip this part.</p>




<p>Next, you&#8217;ll want to explain the background of your problem. Introduce your problem by explaining how you got to it. What were you trying to do what what tools where you using? Explain the scope of the problem so that whoever is helping you knows exactly what was going on. After that you&#8217;ll want to post some actual lines of code so that the person helping you can recreate the problem is need be. Remember that any error messages may also be helpful.</p>




<p>Sometimes when we are asking programming questions we want to jump straight to the error because that&#8217;s what we are focused on. But it is important to present the full scope of the problem because the person we are asking the question to, or any readers online, doesn&#8217;t know exactly what you were doing before you got there.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Do You Take the Punches?]]></title>
    <link href="http://rjmccluskey.github.io/blog/2014/11/07/how-to-do-you-take-the-punches/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-07T12:08:36-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://rjmccluskey.github.io/blog/2014/11/07/how-to-do-you-take-the-punches</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>According to Dr. L. Nathanson, if people do not process shame in a healthy way, they will generally respond to it in one of four defensive directions which he has organized in the <a href="http://southdown.on.ca/publications/articles/Compass-of-Shame.pdf">&#8220;Compass of Shame&#8221;</a>. As shown in the picture below, these four directions are <span class="italic">withdrawal</span>, <span class="italic">attack self</span>, <span class="italic">avoidance</span>, and <span class="italic">attack other</span>. This week, <a href="http://devbootcamp.com">DBC</a> has asked us to examine our lives and ask ourselves how we respond to conflict and shame.</p>


<!-- more -->


<p><img src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-2ylImw4G2g4/Tfs_FpPbAxI/AAAAAAAAAQI/K1vDnBYkShw/s1600/shameu.jpg" class="img-body"></p>

<p>I think that most people have used all four of these defense mechanisms at some point but generally we go to one more often. In the past, I&#8217;ve definitely reacted to shame in the direction of attacking myself. There&#8217;s lots of examples I could give, but to be honest, it&#8217;s a little too personal for me to just spill out for anyone on the Internet to see. Today, I can say that I&#8217;ve gotten a lot better at not doing this and instead learning from any emotional conflict I encounter, but this skill was something that I had to work at. And in a weird way, I think my tenancy to &#8220;attack myself&#8221; actually helped me to improve my ability to process shame. Why do I think this? Well, the way I would attack myself was by blaming myself for the conflict and putting myself down. This is definitely not healthy but it led to a lot of self examination. Of course, examining yourself with the wrong attitude can be very damaging, but luckily I managed to eventually turn it positive.</p>




<p>I used to wonder all the time, what could I have done differently that would have prevented the conflict. Sometimes this would make me blame myself wrongfully, which led to putting myself down. I&#8217;d hold onto the shame, and that sucked. But looking inside myself sparked other discoveries that I think helped me to let go of the shame and look at the experience as a chance to learn and improve myself. Instead of putting myself down, I began to grow stronger.</p>




<p>I&#8217;m not perfect, but I think I&#8217;ve become pretty good at spotting when my mind wants to go down it&#8217;s old path of attacking myself. Being aware of my emotional reactions gives me the ability to see it with a clearer mind and process my emotions more healthily.</p>




<p>So what does this have to do with learning to code? In any field you are going to be working with other people. And when people get together, there tends to be conflict at some point. So I think DBC is trying to help us improve ourselves more than just technically so that we are just better human beings. And as better human beings, we can be better developers!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Do You Value?]]></title>
    <link href="http://rjmccluskey.github.io/blog/2014/11/02/what-do-you-value/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-02T12:03:44-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://rjmccluskey.github.io/blog/2014/11/02/what-do-you-value</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Values. It&#8217;s a word you hear a lot. When we elect government officials we ask &#8220;what are their values?&#8221; Your grandma probably has certain values that she hopes you&#8217;ll keep in your family. And most importantly, did you assign all the right values to your variables?! Okay, just kidding on that last one! But seriously, what do you value most when you are happiest? Personally, I value <span class="italic">ambition</span>.</p>


<!-- more -->


<p>I thought about times when I&#8217;ve been the happiest and most satisfied. Contrary to that, I thought about times when I&#8217;ve been the least satisfied with my life. And I could quickly narrow down the difference in regards to ambition. Right now I can say that I am very happy. I&#8217;ve chosen to change my career and I love what I&#8217;m doing now. A lot of that has to do with me feeling ambitious. I&#8217;m driven to code every single day and learn as much as I can every single day. And it&#8217;s fun! I seriously wake up every morning and get excited to open my laptop and start coding. This ambition has given me a whole new perspective on life and has even improved other aspects. However, before I made the change, I wasn&#8217;t nearly as satisfied. I woke up and went to work because I felt that I <span class="italic">had</span> to. I&#8217;m not saying it was all bad, but I didn&#8217;t feel ambitious like I do now.</p>




<p>Last week I talked about <a href="http://rjmccluskey.github.io/blog/c6-stereotype-threat.html">stereotype threat</a> and how it can get in the way of achieving at your highest level. To recap, it&#8217;s the impostor in your head telling you that you aren&#8217;t good enough for this and that. I think that holding ambition as an important value can help fight against stereotype threat. If you are ambitious, you might take on a lot and you might fail at times, but you will also see yourself succeed in ways others (or even yourself) do not think is possible and that success will prove the impostor wrong. Having a track record of these successes born out of your ambition can be a great thing to fall back on when times get tough.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Stereotypes Are Bad, Mmkay]]></title>
    <link href="http://rjmccluskey.github.io/blog/2014/10/26/stereotypes-are-bad-mmkay/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-26T12:38:20-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://rjmccluskey.github.io/blog/2014/10/26/stereotypes-are-bad-mmkay</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ever heard of <span class="italic">stereotype threat</span>? I hadn&#8217;t before this week but <a href="http://devbootcamp.com">DBC</a> had us research it. It&#8217;s a really interesting topic and I think everyone can benefit from understanding it. So what exactly is it? This <a href="http://www.reducingstereotypethreat.org/definition.html">article</a> explains it well:</p>


<!-- more -->


<blockquote class="quote">Stereotype threat refers to being at risk of confirming, as self-characteristic, a negative stereotype about one&#8217;s group (<a href="http://www.reducingstereotypethreat.org/bibliography_steele_aronson.html">Steele & Aronson, 1995</a>). This term was first used by <a href="http://www.reducingstereotypethreat.org/bibliography_steele_aronson.html">Steele and Aronson (1995)</a> who showed in several experiments that Black college freshmen and sophomores performed more poorly on standardized tests than White students when their race was emphasized. When race was not emphasized, however, Black students performed better and equivalently with White students. The results showed that performance in academic contexts can be harmed by the awareness that one&#8217;s behavior might be viewed through the lens of racial stereotypes.</blockquote>




<p>While this research was done primarily in terms of race, stereotype threat can come in many forms. I noticed a long time before I signed up for DBC that I was interested in coding. I wished I knew it earlier so that I would have chosen to pursue a CS degree when applying to college. So for a while, I didn&#8217;t believe I could switch careers and become a developer. I had already obtained a different degree and was heading on a different path. I know that this might not exactly have been a stereotype holding me back but it&#8217;s the best way I can identify with the subject and I think it&#8217;s something that a lot of us going to DBC have felt before.</p>




<p>Stereotype threat is really that little naysayer inside our brain telling us that we can&#8217;t do something because of x, y, and z. But that evil little voice is wrong! I know without a doubt, a lot if not all of us students will have moments of doubting ourselves while at DBC. And I think the best way to combat this is to pay attention to others and their attitude. If someone seems down on themselves we should reassure them that they are capable! And when we get down on ourselves we should remind ourselves how far we&#8217;ve come and seek help from others. The whole point of DBC is to foster a community to learn with and from. So it will be with this community that we will fight stereotype threat.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
