<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Ruby on Rails | Rich Code]]></title>
  <link href="http://rjmccluskey.github.io/blog/categories/ruby-on-rails/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://rjmccluskey.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-12T12:21:11-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://rjmccluskey.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rich McCluskey]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[So What About Rails?]]></title>
    <link href="http://rjmccluskey.github.io/blog/2014/11/05/so-what-about-rails/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-05T12:10:35-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://rjmccluskey.github.io/blog/2014/11/05/so-what-about-rails</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So up to this point of Phase 0 at <a href="http://devbootcamp.com">DBC</a> I&#8217;ve learned a ton of stuff. I&#8217;m now familiar with git and GitHub, HTML, CSS, Ruby, JavaScript, and even a little bit of SQL. Before I started DBC, I had heard of all these languages except that I never heard or read about Ruby by itself. It was always mentioned as &#8220;Ruby on Rails&#8221;. We won&#8217;t be getting into Rails until the immersive phases but I still want to know more about it since it seems to be so closely tied with Ruby. So let&#8217;s learn about Rails!</p>


<!-- more -->


<p>Stated simply, Ruby on Rails, or just Rails, is an open source web framework written in Ruby. Lots of different companies use RoR including Twitter and Github. Sounds good, except what exactly is a framework? To conceptually understand a framework let&#8217;s look at the frame of a building.</p>


<p><img class="img-body" src="http://www.vermontframes.com/images/page-design-process.jpg"></p>

<p>The framework of this house is not visually appealing and wouldn&#8217;t provide very good shelter by itself, but it is necessary for the structural integrity of the house and all other parts on the house require it before they can be added. It wouldn&#8217;t make very much sense to build just one wall with all the doors, windows, paint, and fixtures before having the frame built. I suppose you could build a house this way but it would take much longer and would be much more difficult.</p>




<p>Just like the wooden frame is used to build a house, a web framework, such as Rails, is used to build web applications. Rails combines Ruby with HTML, CSS, and Javascript and by doing so creates the structure of our web app. Without a framework, we would have to make all these connections ourselves and there would be lots of repetition. Our code would take longer to make, be more prone to bugs, and be harder to implement new things later on.</p>




<p>This is a pretty basic introduction to Rails, but hopefully you at least now know the difference between Ruby and Rails and how they work together. If you are interested to know more, I found a much more in depth article on the subject <a href="http://railsapps.github.io/what-is-ruby-rails.html">here</a>.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
